Preliminary Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office. Records, 1908-2000 and undated RL.00675
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office. records
1908-2000 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office
RL.00675
161 Linear Feet 50,000 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office. Records was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1994-2002.
Historical Note
Company founded in NY in 1864. The J. Walter Thompson company is one of the world's oldest and largest advertising firms.
Collection Overview
This collection (94-110) (27,000 items, 50 linear feet, dated 1908-1989) consists mostly of vertical files, including office newsletters, speeches and writings, publications, training and planning documents from Chicago and other JWT offices. There are also 78 reels of microfilm of Chicago office ads prior to 1970, as well as significant collections of proof files especially pertaining to major clients like Kraft, Quaker Oats, and Schlitz. In addition, the collection holds several hundred "Aber Reports" dating between 1950-1971, which were market research summations of various product categories. A container list for this accession follows below.
Subsequent additions (96-169, 99-130, 99-239) (8514 items; dated 1970-1998) contain an item-level index to the massive library of research reports maintained by JWT's Chicago Office. Materials are arranged in alphabetical order; the largest alphabetical run is by company name. There are also cards for X and AV reports, general research reports, and an index to JWT People Profiles. Also included are printed proceedings from international symposia on magazine readership research for 1981, 1983, 1985, 1988, and 1991, including copies of some of the previously unpublished papers and related printed material (1998). These materials reveal the lengths to which advertisers go to gain insight into consumer thinking. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising and Marketing History. A container list for accession 99-130 follows below.
Addition (01-110) (70 items, .2 lin. ft.; dated [1980s]) consists of about 70 color slides depicting people, events, and locations within the company's Chicago offices.
Addition (02-0188) (397 items, 8.7 linear feet; dated 1980-2000 and undated) comprises primarily information on and examples of Thompson Total Branding (TTB), including in the US, England, Jamaica, and Asia. TTB began in 1996 and is JWT's method for addressing client marketing needs. Also includes copies of earlier methodologies, the T-Plan and Thompson Way; employee manuals; training material; J. Walter University intern/trainee manual (2000); information about the Lintas, McCann-Erickson, and Ogilvy and Mather agencies; material from JWT's World Partners Council meetings (Italy, 1995; Mexico, 1997) and marketing seminars held in the agency's Asia-Pacific region; six 3/4" U-matic SP and 11 VHS videocassettes, mainly of presentations and training material (1980s-1990s); 1 audiocassette; 47 color slides; and 208 electronic documents on 2 CD-ROMs. A container list for this accession follows below.
Several accessions of the JWT Chicago Office Records were completely or partially deaccessioned at the request of the JWT Chicago and returned to the JWT Record Center. These involved proprietary research in which the clients still retained an interest. The accessions involved were: 95-016 (10 boxes); 95-015 (7 boxes); 95-018 (2 boxes); 95-017 (1 box); and 99-0130 (28 boxes). For further information, contact Research Services.
Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising -- Research; Employees -- Training of; Brand name products -- Marketing -- Management; CD-ROMs; Advertising -- Management; Readership surveys; Audiocassettes; Color slides; Advertising -- History; Advertising campaigns; Periodicals -- Circulation; Machine-readable records; Marketing -- Asia; Marketing -- Pacific Area; Videocassettes; Marketing research -- United States; Advertising agencies -- History; J. Walter Thompson Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office
- Accession 1994-0110
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Unpublished materials less than 15 years old are closed to non-JWT researchers.
  - Market Research Department, NYO, Aber Reports, 1950-1963 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    [Research reports on product categories, evidently named for a chief author, Caroline E. Aber]
  - Market Research Department, New York Office, Aber Reports, 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Market Research Department, NYO, Aber Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    [Now produced by the JWT Reference Unit]
  - New York Office Newsletters (unbound), 1945-1965 (Box 4)
  - New York Office Newsletters (unbound), 1965-1983 (Box 5)
  - JWT Media Publications, Various, 1973-1981 (Box 6)
  - JWT News, 1984-1986 (Box 7)
  - JWT London Information Center Book News, 1982-1987 (Box 7)
    [Compiled by Bryan Way]
  - JWT Media Publications, Various, [1980s] (Box 8)
    [Includes Cable Capsules, and Network Notes (Chicago)]
  - Writings and Speeches of JWT Personnel, 1956-1962 (Box 9)
    [Mostly by N. Strouse and A. Johnson]
  - Writings and Speeches of JWT Personnel, 1963-1975 (Box 10)
    [Includes clippings about JWT and JWT personnel]
  - Writings and Speeches of JWT Personnel, 1976-1979 (Box 11)
  - Chicago Office Microfilm, Nos. AD31-AD78, undated (Box 12)
  - Chicago Office Microfilm, Nos. AD1-AD21, AD24-AD30, undated (Box 13)
  - Aunt Jemima Ads, ca. 1989 (Box 14)
    [Includes Packaging, mechanicals, layouts and oversize]
  - Old Binders, [1984] (Box 15)
    [Includes records and contents of Chicago proof books; detailed lists of items filmed in reels AD1-AD78. Also includes some promotional materials, such as coupons for Kraft products.]
  - Color Slides, [1980s] (Box 16)
    [Includes images of ads from Chicago proof books from the early 1900s on for multiple clients. Arranged by client/date per books. Also a binder relating to the records center storage of profs in the 1980s.]
  - Booklet, The Many Worlds of Sam Meek, undated (Box 17)
  - Vertical Files on JWT Offices, [1930s-1980s] (Box 18)
    [Includes, New York, San Francisco, Australia, Belgium, Germany, India, London, and others; miscellaneous newsletters]
  - Vertical Files on Chicago Office, from 1924 on (Box 19)
    [Includes data and plan forms for advertising; files on Chicago office seminars [1970s]; TGI materials]
  - JWT Speeches and Articles, 1971-1978 (Box 20)
  - Chicago Client Summaries, 1969 (Box 20)
  - Communications Plan, 1975-1976 (Box 20)
  - Axiom materials, [ca. 1980] (Box 20)
  - Vertical Files, [ca. 1954-1975] (Box 21)
    [Includes Chicago office files; Communispond; Consumer Panel; Deltakos and other subsidiaries; financial records; compensation]
  - Writings and Speeches, 1958-1970 (Box 22)
  - Publications and Speeches, [1960s-1970s] (Box 23)
    [JWT London, BMRB, South Africa]
  - JWT Junior Forum Talks, 1951-1952 (Box 23)
  - Media Reports (Chicago office), 1970 (Box 23)
  - Chicago Office Account Files, undated (Box 24)
    [Includes research materials, ca. 1950s-1960s]
  - Personnel Lists, undated (Box 24)
  - Training Manual, 1921 (Box 24)
  - Kraft-Phenix Press Releases, [1930s] (Box 24)
  - Writings and Speeches, 1908-1957 (Box 25)
  - Kraft Food Proofs, 1952-1956 (Box 26)
    [Includes trade, newsprint, outdoor, and consumer advertisements]
  - Kraft Food Proofs, 1950-1952 (Box 27)
  - Salada Tea Proofs, 1978 (Box 28)
  - Schlitz Proofs, 1956-1980 (Box 28)
  - Kraft, 1950, 1959 (Box 29)
  - Chicago Economic Development Commission, 1977-1979 (Box 29)
  - Chicago Health Club, 1977 (Box 29)
  - Vic Tanny, undated (Box 29)
  - Quaker Oats, 1954-1959 (Box 29)
  - Kraft Proofs, 1944-1946 (Box 30)
    [3 proof boxes]
  - Kraft Proofs, 1955-1958 (Box 31)
    [2 books in a proof box]
  - Kraft Proofs, 1957-1958 (Box 32)
    [3 proof books]
  - Kraft Proofs, 1947-1951 (Box 33)
- Accession 99-130
  - X Reports RCB 8126 (Box 1)
  - X Reports RCB 8127 (Box 2)
  - X Reports RCB 8128 (Box 3)
  - X Reports RCB 8129 (Box 4)
  - X Reports RCB 8130 (Box 5)
  - X Reports RCB 8132 (Box 6)
  - X Reports RCB 8133 (Box 7)
  - X Reports RCB 8134 (Box 8)
  - X Reports RCB 8135 (Box 9)
  - X Reports RCB 8136 (Box 10)
  - X Reports RCB 8137 (Box 11)
  - X Reports RCB 8138 (Box 12)
  - X Reports RCB 9363 (Box 13)
  - X Reports RCB 9364 (Box 14)
  - X Reports RCB 9365 (Box 15)
  - X Reports RCB 9366 (Box 16)
  - X Reports RCB 9367 (Box 17)
  - X Reports RCB 9368 (Box 18)
  - X Reports RCB 9369 (Box 19)
  - X Reports RCB 9370 (Box 20)
  - X Reports RCB 9371 (Box 21)
  - X Reports RCB 9372 (Box 22)
  - X Reports RCB 9373 (Box 23)
  - X Reports RCB 9374 (Box 24)
  - X Reports RCB 9375 (Box 25)
  - Research Reports RCB 9327 (Box 26)
  - Research Reports: Oscar Meyer RCB 9023 (Box 27)
  - Research Reports: Oscar Meyer RCB 9024 (Box 28)
  - Research Reports: Schlitz RCB 3718 (Box 29)
  - Research Reports: Schlitz RCB 4327 (Box 30)
  - Research Reports: Schlitz RCB 7209 (Box 31)
  - New Business RCB 5996 (Box 32)
  - New Business RCB 8569 (Box 33)
  - New Business RCB 8608 (Box 34)
  - New Business RCB 8609 (Box 35)
  - New Business RCB 9454 (Box 36)
  - Personnel RCB 8883 (Box 37)
  - Personnel RCB 8901 (Box 38)
  - Ameritech RCB 7424 (Box 39)
  - Ameritech RCB 7425 (Box 40)
  - Accounts RCB 2854 (Box 41)
  - Research Reports: Kraft RCB 5509 (Box 42)
  - Research Reports: Kraft RCB 6967 (Box 43)
  - Research Reports: Kraft RCB 7322 (Box 44)
  - Research Reports: Kraft RCB 7828 (Box 45)
  - Research Reports: Kraft RCB 7836 (Box 46)
  - Research Reports: Kraft RCB 8014 (Box 47)
  - Research Reports: Kraft RCB 8015 (Box 48)
  - Research Reports: Sears Hispanic RCB 8570 (Box 49)
  - Research Reports: Sears Hispanic RCB 8575 (Box 50)
  - Employee Handbooks no RCB # (Box 51)
  - RCB 8181 (Box 52)
- Accession 2002-0188
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - Sesame Steet Promotional Items (Box 1)
    - DSN-Ads, DeBeers Diamond [Solitare] case-see white box also (Box 1)
    - Ford Truck-DM (Box 1)
    - DeBeers (Box 1)
    - Client Mailer regarding drug campaign (Box 1)
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    - [Presentations done by James Walker and others in London, 1996] (Box 2)
    - Case studies and presentations, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Early TTB training Presentations developed by J. Furr, D. Baker and others (Box 2)
    - JWT Asia training Program Presentations by Grace Atkinson (Box 2)
    - JWT License plate (Box 2)
    - New Buisiness mailers and promptional pieces from JWT Hong Kong, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Ford Focus Lanch press list (Box 2)
    - TTB case study for JWT affiliate agency in Jamaica (Box 2)
    - Thompson Total Branding: Kraft (Box 2)
    - Work done by JWT Specialized, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - Material from JWT world council, 1995, 3 folders, 3 binders (Box 3)
    - Ogilvy and Mather manual (Box 3)
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    - Welcome box for 1995 world council meeting (Box 4)
    - Expertise and Experience binder (Box 4)
    - Welcome box material for attendees at JWT Partners World Council in 1997, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - JWT informational material, 2 folders, 1 binder (Box 4)
  - Contents of Box 5: (Box 5)
    - Presentation and printed material (Box 5)
    - Material from JWT seminar in Malaysia (Box 5)
    - Japanese Version 2 TTB materials (Box 5)
    - O and M (Box 5)
    - Printed material (Box 5)
    - JWT employee benefits booklet (Box 5)
    - Material used for Asia-Pacific region workshops, 4 spiral binders (Box 5)
  - Contents of Box 6: (Box 6)
    - Board speech and slides (Box 6)
    - Kraft Media Seminar (Box 6)
    - Employee Handbook (Box 6)
    - Workshop material (Box 6)
  - Contents of Box 7: (Box 7)
    - TTB Case Histories, 2, 3/4"U-matic SP videocassettes (Box 7)
    - Tough Brand Cluster video, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 7)
    - 1997 F-Series Spots, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 7)
    - Diamond Solitaire Product Trend, 1 VHS videocassette (Box 7)
    - The Real Thing DSN Compilation Tape, 1 VHS videocassette (Box 7)
    - Dunlop Corbin Communications, 1 VHS videocassette (Box 7)
    - Ford Focus Press Conference, 1 VHS videocassette (Box 7)
    - Thompson Total Branding, 2 VHS videocassettes (Box 7)
    - Einson Freeman, 1 VHS videocassette (Box 7)
    - Kelloggs Rome Presentation, 1 VHS videocassette (Box 7)
    - Nestle, 1 VHS videocassette (Box 7)
  - Contents of Box 8: (Box 8)
    - Thompson Total Branding, 1 VHS videocassete, 1 audio cassette (Box 8)
    - Total Branding cases, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 8)
    - Kellogg, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 8)
    - Nestle, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 8)
    - Worldwide Happy Birthday, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 8)
    - Account videos from 1995 World council meeting, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 8)
    - Bill Thompson, 3, 3/4"U-matic SP videocassettes (Box 8)
  - Contents of Box 9: (Box 9)
    - JWTV Asia Pacific 10EA Round Up, In Rome, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 9)
    - Bill Thompson, Eyes On Thompson, JWT, A Worldwide Powerhouse, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 9)
    - John Furr Presentations, 3, 3/4"U-matic SP videocassettes (Box 9)
    - JWT World Partners Council, 1995, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 9)
    - Eyes On Thompson Presentation, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 9)
    - James Webb Young Workshop, Manila, 1, 3/4" U-matic SP videocassette (Box 9)
  - Contents of Oversized Box 10: (Box 10)
    - Ford packing tube (Box 10)
    - Kraft Recruitment (Box 10)
    - Kelloggs Training Program, 2 binders (Box 10)
    - John Furr's basic training workshop presentation (Box 10)
    - 1997 Ford Expedition Launch (Box 10)
  - Contents of Oversized Box 11: (Box 11)
    - J. Walter University intern/trainee manual, 2000 (Box 11)
    - Ford (Box 11)
    - Recruitment Advertising manual (Box 11)
  - Contents of Oversized Box 12: (Box 12)
    - Thompson Total Branding (Box 12)
    - Ford Calendar (Box 12)
  - Contents of Oversized Box 13: (Box 13)
    - Welcome box from 1997 Partners World Council (Box 13)